William Field Staunton papers, 1852-1947
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
William Field Staunton papers, 1937-1952
AZ 152
Staunton, William Field
Correspondence, diaries, financial records, photographs, newspaper clippings, maps, and other papers, relating to mining and Staunton's personal activities in Arizona and California. Personal papers consist of diaries, notebooks, photographs and his memoirs. Mining records which include correspondence, reports, newspaper clippings, photographs, blueprints, maps, and articles by Staunton form the bulk of the collection.
3 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL:http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Mining Engineer in Arizona and California. Staunton was mill and mine superintendent at the Tombstone Mill & Mining Co., Charleston, Ariz. from 1885 to 1894, superintendent of the Congress (Ariz.) Gold Co. 1894 to 1910. He was also general manager of the Tombstone Consolidated Mines Co. 1901 to 1910; vice-president and general manager of the Imperial Copper Co., Silverbell, Ariz., and of the Arizona Southern Railroad Co. from 1903 to 1910; and held those positions in the Southern Arizona Smelting Co., Sasco, Ariz. during 1904 to 1910.
In 1910, in Los Angeles, he established a consulting practice to develop oil and copper properties in Arizona and California. In 1911 he became vice-president, treasurer, and later president of Calumet Oil Co., Los Angeles, and president of the Verde Central Mines, Inc., Jerome, Ariz.
Organization
This collection is organized into three series:
Series I: Personal and Family Papers, 1852-1947
Series II: Mining Papers, 1879-1938
Series III: Mining Photographs, Blueprints, and Maps, 1910-1938
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, diaries, financial records, photographs, newspaper clippings, maps, and other papers, relating to mining and Staunton's personal activities in Arizona and California. Personal papers consist of diaries, notebooks, photographs and his memoirs. Mining records which include correspondence, reports, newspaper clippings, photographs, blueprints, maps, and articles by Staunton form the bulk of the collection. Correspondents include Frank M. Murphy, V.L. Mason, Henry M. Robinson, and James S. Douglas.
Access Terms
Staunton, William Field, -- 1860-1947 -- Archives
Douglas, James Stuart, -- 1868-1949 -- Correspondence
Robinson, Henry Mauris, -- 1868-1937 -- Correspondence
Murphy, Frank Morrell, -- 1855-1917 -- Correspondence
Tombstone Mill and Mining Company -- Records and correspondence
Tombstone Consolidated Mines Company -- Records and correspondence
Congress Gold Company -- Records and correspondence
Congress Consolidated Mines Company -- Records and correspondence
Western Land and Cattle Company -- Records and correspondence
Mines and mineral resources -- Arizona -- Cochise County -- History -- Sources
Mines and mineral resources -- Arizona -- Pima County -- History -- Sources
Mines and mineral resources -- Arizona -- Yavapai County -- History -- Sources
Mines and mineral resources -- Arizona -- Yavapai County -- History -- Sources
Mines and mineral resources -- Arizona -- Yavapai County -- History -- Sources
Copper mines and mining -- Arizona -- History -- Sources
Gold mines and mining -- Arizona -- History -- Sources
Silver mines and mining -- Arizona -- History -- Sources
Railroads -- Arizona -- History -- Sources
Railroad passes -- Specimens
Ostrich farming -- Arizona -- History -- Sources
Photoprints
Photographs
Maps
Blueprints
Correspondence
Diaries
Container List
- Series I: Personal and Family Papers, 1852-1947
  - Diaries, Diary of European Trip, Diary Index, Memoirs. 1852-1947 (Box 1)
  - Personal and Biographical Material (commencement programs, awards, memberships, marriage record). 1852-1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Family Papers (mostly relating to father). 1904-1929 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes:
    "W.F. Staunton: His Scrap Book"
    "Sundry Writings by W.F. Staunton"
    Railroad Passes
    Automobile Notebook
    Radio Notebook
    "Petit Dictionnaire Française"
    Calumet Oil Company
    Zenda Gold Mining Company
    Notes on Old Income Tax Returns, 1913-1929
    Notes on Smelting, Ore Contracts, Pumping Machiner, Sundry Prices, 1904
    "Sundry Old Notes from 1904"
    French Grammar
    "Current" (various notes, personal, financial, reading lists, magazine subscriptions).
    Miscellaneous Notes, 1910-1912 (mostly financial and concerning the Pan-american Ostrick Company and Calumet Oil Company).
    Geological Notes
    Envelope of Miscellaneous Notes, Addresses, Cards.
  - Correspondence: Frank M. Murphy. 1897-1910 (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
  - Correspondence: V.L. Mason. 1903-1911 (Box 3, Folder 6-8)
  - Correspondence: Henry M. Robinson. 1903-1921, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence: Miscellaneous. 1882-1938 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - Correspondence: Miscellaneous "R." (Note: This folder is apparently a fragment of a longer alphabetical file covering the 1920s and 1930s. It has been retained intact to indicate the probable scope of missing correspondence for this period.) 1921-1938 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series II: Mining Papers, 1879-1938
  - Tombstone Mill and Mining Company (miscellaneous papers) 1879-1901 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Tombstone Mill and Mining Company (reports). 1881-1895 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Tombstone Consolidated Mines Company (miscellaneous papers). 1901-1910 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Congress Gold Company & Congress Consolidated Mines Company (miscellaneous papers). (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Tombstone Pumps and Water Situation. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Clippings and Articles: Tombstone. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Clippings & Articles: Jerome. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Clippings & Articles: Copper Tariff. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Clippings & Articles: Colorado River. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series III: Mining Photographs, Blueprints, and Maps, 1910-1938
  - Photographs: Congress. 1910-1938 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Photographs: Jerome. 1910-1938 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Photographs: Silverbell and Sasco. 1910-1938 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Photographs: Tombstone. 1910-1938 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Photographs: California (Balboa, Los Angeles) Puget Sound, Arizona. 1910-1938 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Western Land & Cattle Company-Correspondence (successor to Pan-American Ostrich Company). 1914-1925 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Western Land & Cattle Company (financial papers). 1914-1928 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Photographs and Maps. 1910-1938 (Box 7)
    Photograph: Congress Gold Mining Company's Works
    Photograph: Staunton's House in Tombstone
    Photograph: Staunton's House in Congress (?)
    Photograph: Staunton (?)
    Mining Maps and Blueprints: Congress Mine
    Mining Maps and Blueprints: Tombstone
    Mining Maps and Blueprints: Silverbell
    Mining Maps and Blueprints: Unidentified